Guide to the Elizabeth Lee Buckingham Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Elizabeth Lee Buckingham papers
1900-1970
SC0167
Buckingham, Elizabeth Lee, 1885-
6.5 Linear feet
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Elizabeth Buckingham, 1977; transferred from Manuscript Division to University Archives.
Information about Access
None.
Separated Materials
Frances T. and Frank Russell material (put in SC 166)
Miscellaneous Christmas cards with no messages on them (discarded)
Recipes (discarded)
Multiple copies of examinations and other mimeographed material (discarded)
BIOGRAPHY
Elizabeth Lee Buckingham was born on November 9, 1885. Her personal history is sketchy due to a lack of concrete information, but she listed Palo Alto as her home town in the 1904-05 Stanford Register. She received her A.B. in 1910 and her A.M. in 1914 from Stanford, both in English. During 1908-09 she was an Assistant in English at Castilleja School in Palo Alto, and during 1910-11 an Assistant in English at Stanford, after which she was on the Stanford faculty continuously until her retirement as Associate Professor of Speech and Drama, Emeritus, in 1944. During many of her years at Stanford she shared a house at 534 Lasuen with several Stanford faculty women, among them Frances Theresa Russell, Mary Yost, and Edith Mirrielees.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
The General Files section contains material on various subjects of interest to Miss Buckingham, a small amount of Stanford-related correspondence, and ten folders of personal correspondence. Any professional correspondence is filed under the appropriate subject heading (Radio, Speech, etc.). The Student Notes are Miss Buckingham's own from her student days, ranging from high school to post-graduate work at Columbia University. The Courses section includes her students' papers and examinations, class notebooks, and some of her own course notes. The folder in the Photographs section includes miscellaneous photographs and negatives, most of them unidentified. One photo of interest is a snapshot of Miss Buckingham with Frances Theresa Russell and Mary Yost, n.d.
The materials in this collection arrived in complete disarray. Letters, course papers, photographs, manuscripts and notebooks were dumped together with recipes, Christmas cards, and scraps of paper with notes and jottings. After the sorting process was well underway it became apparent that some of the papers were the property of Frances Theresa Russell, Stanford Professor of English, and her husband Frank Russell, a noted Harvard anthropologist who died in 1903. Mrs. Russell and Miss Buckingham were housemates for many years until Mrs. Russell's death in 1936, and apparently Mrs. Russell's papers had never been sorted or claimed. Every attempt has been made to identify and separate the material. The Russell papers have been put in SC 166. However, a researcher should be aware of the difficulty and bring any questionable items to the attention of the Archivist.
There is no evidence that Miss Buckingham carried on professional correspondence with anyone over a long period of time. However, her personal correspondence includes descriptive letters from a number of her students who were struggling to become professionally established. There are also several hand-tinted Christmas cards, some with notes, from Mrs. Bruce Bliven, 1936-40. It is helpful to know when examining the correspondence that Miss Buckingham's nickname was Peter. Mrs. Russell was often referred to as "Terri". Mary Yost, Dean of Women and Lecturer in English, signed her letters "Wendy". Letters signed by "Edith" are from Edith Mirrielees, Professor of English.
Arrangement note
These papers are arranged into four major groups: General Files, 1904-70; Student Notes, 1900-18; Courses, 1911-44, and Photographs, n.d. While the papers range from 1900-1970, the bulk of the collection falls within the period 1930-43.
Access Terms
Bliven, Bruce, 1916-2002.; Buckingham, Elizabeth Lee, 1885-; Mirrielees, Edith.; Russell, Frances Theresa,, 1873-1936.; Russell, Frank,, 1868-1903.; Stanford University. Department of English. -- General subdivision--Faculty.;; Stanford University. Department of Speech and Drama. -- General subdivision--Faculty.;; Yost, Mary.
Collection Contents
- GENERAL FILES, 1904-70
  - Book and play lists; bibliographies, 1920's and 1930's (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Book and play lists; bibliographies, 1920's and 1930's (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Book and play lists; bibliographies, 1920's-1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Book and play lists - bibliography of Stanford holdings of one-act plays, author index, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Book and play lists - bibliography of Stanford holdings of one-act plays, title index and key list, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Book and play lists - plays for school production, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - California Council for Speech Education, (Includes some correspondence), 1939 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Conferences - Curriculum and Instruction, Stanford, Curriculum, Jun 25-30, 1934; 1936 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Conferences - Speech and Drama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, personal, 1906-34 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, personal, (See also f.19), 1935-36 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, personal, 1937-38 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, personal, 1939-40 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, personal, 1941-42 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, personal, 1943-61 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, personal, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, personal - Frank Russell's library, disposition of -, 1936, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, personal - business matters, (Includes Buckingham's real estate interests), 1930-70 and undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondences personal - sympathy letters re. death of Mrs. Russell, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Costumes and Makeup - handbook by Helen Green, 1941; (Inscribed copy) (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Drama - miscellaneous clippings, 1925-42 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Drama - miscellaneous material, (Includes some correspondence), 1918-40 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Drama - scripts, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Drama - scripts, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Drama - scripts, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - English - miscellaneous material, (Includes some correspondence), 1911-43 and undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Exams - Interpretation, preliminary M.A., Jul-41 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Exams, miscellaneous, 1907-11 and undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - "The Fundamental Course in Speech for California High Schools" - recommendations of the Kersey Committee, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Memorial Auditorium, (Includes some correspondence), 1934-39 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous material, 1908-47 and undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous material, 1930-47 and undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Motion Picture Science, 1934 and undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Peace and pacifism, miscellaneous material re., 1919-37 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Poetry - manuscripts, n.d. (Some by Buckingham, others unidentified) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Poetry - miscellaneous material re., 1918 and undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Programs and concerts Buckingham attended, musical, 1914-37 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Programs and concerts Buckingham attended, musical, 1914-37 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Programs and concerts Buckingham attended, musical, 1914-37 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Published articles by Buckingham -, 1904, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Questionnaires on theater, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Radio - correspondence, 1938-42 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Radio - miscellaneous material, including scripts, (See also Writers' War Board, f. 30), 1940-43 and undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Radio - miscellaneous material, including scripts, 1941-44 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Sheridan, Helen Courtney - poems, paper P.S. 200, letter, 1930's and undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Speech (Public Speaking) - correspondence, 1933-43 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Speech (Public Speaking) - miscellaneous material, 1932-41 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Stanford University - division matters, including some correspondence, 1932-42 and undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Stanford University - miscellaneous material, including some correspondence, 1925-45 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Stanford University - miscellaneous material re. students of Buckingham, 1934-41 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - "Stanford Writers in the Saturday Evening Post" - TLS, Archie Rice to R.L. Wilbur, 4-Apr-42 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Western Assn. of Teachers of Speech - notes, draft of Buckingham speech., (1933?) (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Word notes and miscellaneous jottings, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Word notes and miscellaneous jottings, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Word notes and miscellaneous jottings, (in envelope titled "Gallery of Players"), 1940's and undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - World War Two - general material, including personal items, (Includes TLS from Pearl S. Buck re. East-West Assn., 1941-44 and undated Mar 24, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - WPA (Works Progress Administration) - Federal Theater Project, 1938 and undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Writers' War Board (including scripts, some correspondence), 1938-43 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Writers' War Board - scripts, 1944-45 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- STUDENT NOTES, 1900-18 AND undated
  - 1900-02 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - 1904-05 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - 1907 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - 1908 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - 1909 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - 1909 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1909 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1909-10 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 1909-10 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 1911-12 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 1911-12 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 1913-14 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - 1916 summer (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - 1916-17 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - 1917-18 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - 1917-18 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - 1917-18 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - 1917-18 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - 1917-18 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - n.d. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - n.d. (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - n.d. (Box 3, Folder 17)
- COURSES, 1911-44
  - Advanced Acting 161, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Aesthetics course not listed in Catalog), (1941? (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Children's Plays 189, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Dramatic Criticism 162 & 194, 1930's (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Dramas for Production 207, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - High School & College Dramatics 195, 1938-39 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - High School & College Dramatics 118, 119b, Ed.217, 1930's (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - High School & College Dramatics - n.d., no course #. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - History of English Drama 170, 251, 252., 1918-30 and undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - History of English Literature - miscellaneous courses, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - History of Interpretative Reading 180, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - History of the Theater 109, 1917-18 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - History of the Theater 109, 1917-18 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - History of the Theater 109, 190, 1930-31 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - History of the Theater 109, 190, 1931 and nd (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - History of the Theater 109, 190, 1931 and undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - History of the Theater 109, 190, 1935 and undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - History of the Theater 109, 190, 1935 and undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - History of the Theater 109, 190, 1930's (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - History of the Theater 109, 190, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - History of the Theater 109, 190, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - History of the Theater 109, 190, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - History of the Theater 109, 190, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - History of the Theater 109, 190, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Interpretation 207, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Interpretation of Modern Drama 144, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Interpretation of Poetry 40, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Miscellaneous unidentified course material, 1938 and undated (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - The One Act Play 158, 159, 1918-36 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Play Production 208, 209, 18a, 1923-36 and undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Play Production 208, [Includes Theater Workshop, no course #, 1930 1928 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Public Speaking 191 [no course name given], 1937 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Radio Speaking 18, 1939-43 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Radio Speaking 18, 1939-43 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Reading & Staging Plays 209, 18a, 1923-39 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Reading & Staging Plays 209, 18a, 1923-39 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Shakespeare, Vocal [Oral] Interpretation of, 157, 1940 and undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Teachers' Reading Course 200c, 1928 and undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Vocal Expression 10, [Also notes for Rhetoric, no course # or date], 1932-40 and undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
- PHOTOGRAPHS
  - Miscellaneous photographs and negatives, most of them unidentified. Includes snapshot of E. Buckingham, F.T. Russell, and M. Yost, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 7)